National Visionary Leadership Project Interviews and Conference Collection AFC 2004/007
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series III: Interviews
  - Joseph Lowery oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2003-01-07, AFC 2004/007: 073
    - Moving Images, 7 videocassettes of 7 (Betacam SP) (210 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 073.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 073.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 073.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 073.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 073.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 073.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 073.MV.007
  - Leatrice McKissack oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2002-02-19, AFC 2004/007: 074
    Leatrice McKissack was the CEO of McKissack & McKissack, Architects & Engineers, Inc., the oldest African American architecture firm in the nation.
    The interview includes Leatrice McKissack's memories of growing up in Missouri and Nashville, Tennessee and attending Fisk University. She recalls her teaching career, raising her daughters and taking over her husband's business, McKissack & McKissack, Architects & Engineers, Inc., after he became ill. She discusses racial discrimination against her firm, successful projects and working with her daughters at the firm.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655539
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (61 pages) (Box-folder 9/94)
    - Graphic Images, 2 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in. (Box-folder 28/394)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 074.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 074.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 074.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 074.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 074.MV.005
  - Adele McQueen oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2003-01-16, AFC 2004/007: 075
    Adele McQueen was a teacher and professor of early childhood education.
    The interview includes Adele McQueen's memories of growing up in Texas and Kansas and attending the Tuskegee Institute, where she helped care for George Washington Carver. She discusses her first teaching job at a boarding school in Alabama, directing the Tuskegee Nursery School and teaching in Liberia while her husband worked for USAID. She discusses her career at Howard University directing a preschool and teaching early child education courses, and starting the organization Housing Unlimited.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655548
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (87 pages) (Box-folder 9/95)
    - Graphic Images, 3 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in. (Box-folder 28/395)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 075.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 075.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 075.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 075.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 075.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 075.MV.006
  - James Meredith oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2006-06-27, AFC 2004/007: 076
    James Meredith was the first African American student to attend the University of Mississippi.
    The interview includes James Meredith's memories of growing up in Kosciusko, Mississippi, serving in the air force and attending Jackson State University. He recalls his friendship with Medgar Evers, applying to the University of Mississippi and the resulting Supreme Court case that allowed him to attend. He discusses his opposition to the non-violence movement and working for Senator Jesse Helms.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2011655235
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (126 pages) (Box-folder 9/96)
    - Graphic Images, 9 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 28/396)
  - Norma Miller oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2006-06-01, AFC 2004/007: 077
    Norma Miller was a swing dancer, actress and stand up comedienne.
    The interview includes Norma Miller's memories of growing up in Harlem, New York, taking dance lessons and dancing the Lindy Hop at the Savoy Ballroom at age 12. She recalls dancing in competitions in New York, touring Europe and her friendship with dancer Frankie Manning. She discusses appearing in movies, the decline of swing dancing, and her later career as a comedienne with Redd Foxx.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655284
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (141 pages) (Box-folder 10/97)
    - Graphic Images, 45 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 28/397)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 077.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 077.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 077.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 077.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 077.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 077.MV.006
  - Arthur Mitchell oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-08-26, AFC 2004/007: 078
    Arthur Mitchell was a ballet dancer, teacher and founder of the Dance Theatre of Harlem.
    The interview includes Arthur Mitchell's memories of growing up in Harlem, New York and attending the High School of Performing Arts where he studied tap and modern dance. He recalls the discrimination against African American dancers, joining Katherine Dunham's dance school and attending the School of American Ballet. He discusses being the first African American in the New York City Ballet, working with choreographer George Balanchine and founding the Dance Theatre of Harlem.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655540
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (74 pages) (Box-folder 10/98)
    - Graphic Images, 52 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 28/398)
    - Moving Images, 7 videocassettes of 7 (Betacam SP) (210 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 078.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 078.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 078.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 078.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 078.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 078.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 078.MV.007
  - Ella Mitchell oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-05-24, AFC 2004/007: 079a
    Ella Mitchell was a Baptist minister, writer and teacher.
    The interview includes Ella Mitchell's memories of growing up in South Carolina, attending Talladega College and Union Theological Seminary where she met her husband, Henry Mitchell. She recalls their move to California, her teaching career in early childhood education and her involvement in the civil rights movement. She discusses the opposition to women clergy in the Baptist Church, her ordination and career as a minister. She is also interviewed with her husband Henry about their marriage and life in the church.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655549
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (42 pages) (Box-folder 10/99)
    - Graphic Images, 5 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in. (Box-folder 28/399)
    - Moving Images, 7 videocassettes of 7 (Betacam SP) (210 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 079a.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 079a.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 079a.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 079a.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 079a.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 079a.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 079b.MV.001
  - Parren Mitchell oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2005-04-21, AFC 2004/007: 080
    Parren Mitchell was the first African American U.S. Congressman from Maryland.
    The interview includes Parren Mitchell's memories of growing up in Baltimore and protesting segregated businesses with his brother Clarence. He recalls his army service in Italy during World War II and after attending Morgan State University, becoming the first African American graduate student at the University of Maryland. He discusses his election to U.S. Congress and sponsoring legislation to support African American businesses.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655510
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (30 pages) (Box-folder 10/100)
    - Graphic Images, 57 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 28/400)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (DVCAM) (64 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 080.MV.001
  - James Moody oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2004-05-24, AFC 2004/007: 081
    James Moody was a jazz saxophonist and band leader.
    The interview includes James Moody's memories of growing up in New Jersey and joining the Air Force, where he learned to play saxophone. He recalls meeting Dizzy Gillespie while in the military and joining his band later in New York. He discusses living in Europe and the forming his own band when he returned to the United States. He also discusses meeting his wife, his opinions on music and advice for young people.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655527
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (42 pages) (Box-folder 10/101)
    - Graphic Images, 26 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 28/401)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 081.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 081.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 081.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 081.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 081.MV.005
  - Toni Morrison oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2004-11-05, AFC 2004/007: 082
    Toni Morrison was an editor, novelist, professor and the first African American to win the Nobel Prize for Literature.
    The interview includes Toni Morrison's memories of growing up in Ohio, attending Howard University and performing with the Howard University Players. She recalls her career at Random House, where she worked as a textbook editor and sought out African American writers. She discusses her writing process, the influence of African American history and slavery on her novels, teaching at Princeton University and the future of African American literature.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655550
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (73 pages) (Box-folder 10/102)
    - Graphic Images, 1 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color; 37 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in. (Box-folder 28/402)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 082.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 082.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 082.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 082.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 082.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 082.MV.006
  - Bob Moses oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2006-06-28, AFC 2004/007: 083
    Bob Moses was a civil rights activist with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and later founded the Algebra Project.
    The interview includes Bob Moses' memories of growing up in Harlem, New York and attending Hamilton College and Harvard University. He discusses teaching math in New York and becoming involved in the civil rights movement and the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). He recalls working with Amzie Moore on the Mississippi Freedom Project and founding the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655470
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (166 pages) (Box-folder 10/103)
    - Graphic Images, 9 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 28/403)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; 7 videocassettes of 7 (DVCAM) (280 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 083.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 083.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 083.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 083.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 083.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 083.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 083.MV.007; AFC 2004/007: 083.MV.008
  - Constance Baker Motley oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2002-01-21, AFC 2004/007: 084
    Constance Baker Motley was a civil rights lawyer with the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, a New York State Senator, and the first African American female federal judge.
    The interview includes Constance Baker Motley's memories of growing up in Connecticut, her family history in Nevis, and attending New York University and Columbia Law School. She discusses her start at the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund clerking for Thurgood Marshall, and her later work with the organization on civil rights cases related to school desegregation. She also discusses attending the March on Washington in 1963.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655471
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (45 pages); 1 bound transcript (91 pages) with CD insert (Box-folder 10/104-105)
    - Graphic Images, 18 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 28/404)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DVCAM) (184 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 084.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 084.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 084.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 084.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 084.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 084.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 084.MV.007
  - Fayard Nicholas oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2003-08-07, AFC 2004/007: 085
    Fayard Nicholas was a tap dancer, actor and choreographer who performed with his brother Harold as the Nicholas Brothers.
    The interview includes Fayard Nicholas' memories of growing up in Philadelphia and watching his parents perform as musicians at the Stanton Theater. He recalls learning to tap dance, developing a show with his brother Harold and performing at New York City nightclubs. He discusses their career as the Nicholas Brothers and working with many famous actors and musicians in Hollywood musicals and Broadway shows.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655492
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (54 pages) (Box-folder 10/106)
    - Graphic Images, 36 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in. (Box-folder 28/405)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DVCAM) (184 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 085.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 085.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 085.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 085.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 085.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 085.MV.006
  - Gil Noble oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2004-08-09, AFC 2004/007: 086
    Gil Noble was a television reporter and documentary filmmaker.
    The interview includes Gil Noble's memories of growing up in Harlem, New York, his participation in the civil rights movement, and his first jobs as a reporter on radio and television. He recalls covering the civil rights movement and urban riots, and starting his television program "Like It Is." He discusses African Americans in the media, reporting on issues in Africa and ethics in journalism.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655289
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (62 pages) (Box-folder 10/107)
    - Graphic Images, 28 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/406)
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (Betacam SP) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 086.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 086.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 086.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 086.MV.004
  - Buck O'Neil oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2003-08-11, AFC 2004/007: 087
    Buck O'Neil was a baseball player for the Kansas City Monarchs and the first African American coach in the major leagues.
    The interview includes Buck O'Neil's memories of growing up in Florida and attending Edward Waters College. He recalls playing baseball for barnstorming teams and facing discrimination in hotels and restaurants. He discusses meeting his wife, serving in the navy during World War II and his career in the Negro Leagues with the Kansas City Monarchs. He also discusses his friendships with Jackie Robinson and Satchel Paige and starting the RBI program for inner-city youth.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655493
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (46 pages) (Box-folder 10/108)
    - Graphic Images, 35 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 4 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/407)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 087.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 087.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 087.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 087.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 087.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 087.MV.006
  - Odetta oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2003-05-26, AFC 2004/007: 088
    Odetta was a folk singer and civil rights activist.
    The interview includes Odetta's memories of growing up in Birmingham, Alabama and Los Angeles, California, where she started to take voice lessons. She recalls performing in San Francisco, meeting other folk singers and dropping her last name. She discusses several albums and performances, and the importance of music to the civil rights movement.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655511
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (29 pages) (Box-folder 10/109)
    - Graphic Images, 5 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/408)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (Betacam SP) (90 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DV) (186 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 088.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 088.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 088.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 088.MV.004
  - Gordon Parks oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2001-11-05, AFC 2004/007: 089
    Gordon Parks was a photographer, writer and filmmaker.
    The interview includes Gordon Parks' memories of growing up in Fort Scott, Kansas, which was the basis for his novel and film The Learning Tree. He discusses moving to St. Paul, Minnesota where he met his wife and worked as a waiter. He recalls buying a camera, getting his first photography job at a department store and working as a documentary photographer for the Farm Security Administration. He also discusses his work in fashion photography, Life Magazine and documenting poverty in Brazil.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655494
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (60 pages); 1 bound transcript (107 pages) with CD insert (Box-folder 11/110-111)
    - Graphic Images, 16 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/409)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DVCAM) (184 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 089.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 089.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 089.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 089.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 089.MV.005
  - Frank Petersen oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2005-05-16, AFC 2004/007: 090
    Frank Petersen was the first African American aviator and general in the Marine Corps.
    The interview includes Frank Petersen's memories of growing up in Topeka, Kansas and serving in the Navy during the Korean War. He recalls the Naval Aviation Cadet Program, discrimination in the military, and joining the Marine Corps as a career officer. He discusses serving in the Vietnam War, recruiting minorities for the marines and becoming the first African American general in the Marine Corps.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655293
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (95 pages) (Box-folder 11/112)
    - Graphic Images, 2 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/410)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (DVC) (184 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 090.MV.001
  - Sidney Poitier oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2004-10-27, AFC 2004/007: 091
    Sidney Poitier was an actor, director, producer and writer.
    The interview includes Sidney Poitier's memories of growing up in the Bahamas, dropping out of school as a child to work and moving to New York on his own. He recalls working as a dishwasher, serving in the army and his first unsuccessful auditions at the American Negro Theater. He discusses his success on Broadway, traveling to South Africa, and his more famous roles that broke down barriers in Hollywood for African Americans.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655294
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (58 pages) (Box-folder 11/113)
    - Graphic Images, 19 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 3 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/411)
    - Moving Images, 9 videocassettes of 9 (Betacam SP) (270 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.007; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.008; AFC 2004/007: 091.MV.009
  - Alvin Poussaint oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2005-05-19, AFC 2004/007: 092
    Alvin Poussaint was a psychiatrist specializing in African American mental health.
    The interview includes Alvin Poussaint's memories of growing up in Harlem, New York, his childhood illness and going to Camp Wochica for the children of leftists. He recalls attending Columbia University and Cornell University Medical School, his brother's drug addiction and mental illness, his efforts to desegregate hospitals and working in a medical clinic for civil rights workers in Mississippi. He discusses the march to support James Meredith, rifts within the civil rights movement, and his work as a consultant for the Cosby Show.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655551
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (107 pages) (Box-folder 11/114)
    - Graphic Images, 45 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/412)
    - Moving Images, 7 videocassettes of 7 (Betacam SP) (210 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 092.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 092.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 092.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 092.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 092.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 092.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 092.MV.007
  - Ernesta Procope oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-04-08, AFC 2004/007: 093
    Ernesta Procope was an insurance agent, real estate broker and the first African American owner of a Wall Street business.
    The interview includes Ernesta Procope's memories of growing up in Brooklyn, New York, taking piano lessons and meeting her husband. She recalls her start as a real estate agent, starting her own insurance company, E.G. Bowman and lobbying for a state law that barred insurance companies from denying coverage to minorities. She discusses working with the New York Housing Authority, moving her business to Wall Street, and her opinions on affirmative action.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655296
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (54 pages) (Box-folder 11/115)
    - Graphic Images, 10 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/413)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (Betacam SP) (90 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 093.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 093.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 093.MV.003
  - Charles Rangel oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-04-07, AFC 2004/007: 094
    Charles Rangel was a lawyer and U.S. Congressman from New York.
    The interview includes Charles Rangel's memories of growing up in Harlem, New York and his first jobs. He recalls his army service in Korea and later attending college and law school in New York. He discusses becoming a U.S. Attorney and running against Adam Clayton Powell for U.S. Congress. He also discusses the changes in New York City, passing the Empowerment Zone Act and his opposition to the Iraq War.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655512
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (67 pages) (Box-folder 11/116)
    - Graphic Images, 43 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 4 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 29/414)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DV) (186 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 094.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 094.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 094.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 094.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 094.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 094.MV.006
  - Della Reese oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-05-21, AFC 2004/007: 095
    Della Reese was an actress, singer and minister.